A Guide to the Papers of Jean Dobler, 1913-1939
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Jean Dobler 1913-1939
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
14051
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by Michael Desrosiers (University of Virginia Class of 1981) of Charleston, South Carolina in memory of his father, Russell Desrosiers, and by Martha (Falconi) Desrosiers of Reston, Virginia, in memory of her mother, Maria Gloria Serrano Checa Falconi, on October 18, 2007.
Custodial History
Maria Gloria Serrano Checa Falconi was the personal secretary for Mr. Dobler while he was serving in Ecuador. Upon her death, the papers passed into the possession of her daughter, Martha Falconi, who married Jim Desrosiers, and subsequently she gave them to his father, Russell Desrosiers. Upon Russell Desrosiers' death, his wife, Eva Fisch Desrosiers, allowed them to go to her son, Michael Desrosiers.
Biographical/Historical Information
Jean Dobler was Charge d'Affaire de la Republique Francaise in Tokyo, Japan, 1930-1931; French consul-general in Cologne, 1934-1937; and a consular official in Quito, 1938-1940.
According to University of Virginia History Professor Stephen A. Schuker, Dobler's service in Cologne coincided with the Nazi repudiation of the disarmament clauses of the Treaty of Versailles, their planning for a 36-division offensive army, and the remilitarization of the Rhineland. From his post at Cologne, Dobler was in an ideal spot to observe the rearmament of the Ruhr and the Rhineland, and his warnings in his dispatches were usually correct. Unfortunately, the French government did not heed his warnings about what was about to transpire in Europe. After the war, Dobler was asked to testify at the French Parliamentary inquiry.
During the march on Paris by the Germans in 1940, many of the original documents from the Ministère des Affaires ètrangères were burned in the courtyard of the Quai d'Orsay. The documents in the French embassy in Berlin also did not survive the war so this collection may well have the only surviving copies of some of Dobler's reports from Cologne.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the diplomatic papers of Jean Dobler, a member of the French foreign service, 1915, 1928-1939, ca. 1,038 items, 4 Hollinger boxes (ca. 1.5 linear feet). Dobler's papers cover the period leading up to World War II when he was stationed in Tokyo, Japan (1929-1931); in Cologne, Germany (1934-1937); and in Quito, Ecuador, 1938-1940. Dobler's posting in Ecuador was his last post prior to the Nazi invasion of France and the establishment of the collaborationist Vichy government.
Several authors discussing the French diplomatic corps at this critical time in history register Dobler's complaints that his dispatches describing the growing strength of Hitler seemed to be ignored by his superiors.
The bulk of the papers are carbon copies of papers sent to the Ministère des Affaires ètrangères; other items include some letters, pamphlets, news clippings, a few articles, and calling cards of visitors.
Arrangement
Both the folders and the papers within the folders are arranged in chronological order.
Contents List
- Manuscript of La Veritable Pensée de L'Alliance Anglo-Japonaise by [Count Tadasu Hayashi?], 1913 August, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Copy of Convencion-Neutralidad Maritima, held in Havana, Cuba, 1928 February, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Telegrams from Tokyo, chiefly including information on political events in Japan, 1929 May-December, 48 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Letters to Japanese Officials, mainly including brief bureaucratic information, 1929 December-1930 June, 19 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
- Letters to the French Foreign Minister from Tokyo, mainly conveying details on political events and popular opinions, 1929 December-1930 November, 20 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
- Telegrams from Tokyo, chiefly containing information on political events, popular attitudes, and code changes, 1930 January-November, 87 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Handwritten Notes and Drafts, 1930 January-September, 9 items. (Box 1:7)
- Letters to Jean Dobler, addressing telegram issues, from Jean Millot and T. Mitani, 1930 February-July, 2 items. (Box 1:8)
- Secret Letters to the French Foreign Minister from Tokyo, including details on Japanese elections (February 26), the impact of Gandhi (March 21), the ruling elite (April 21), and growing industrialism (June 14), 1930 February-September, 8 items. (Box-folder 1:9)
- Handwritten Copy of History of the Japanese Students' Thought Movements by Kenji Sugiyama, 1930 October, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:10)
- Tables Describing Students in Japanese Schools, 1930, 13 items. (Box-folder 1:11)
- Handwritten Research on Socialism, including counts of socialist books in libraries and lists of philosophers, 1930, 11 items. (Box-folder 1:12)
- Notes to the Following French Minister, 1931 September-December, 3 items. (Box-folder 1:13)
  Includes information on the Japanese people, leaders, and political situations.
- Letter on Conversation with Yamamoto, who was part of the Seiyukai Party and exercised a powerful influence on Japanese politics, 1933 May, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:14)
- Letters to the French Foreign Minister from Cologne, 1934 January-March 16, 9 items. (Box-folder 1:15)
  Includes information on religious opposition of the Nazi Party (January 15, March 16), popular opinions in the Rhine region (January 30, February 15), indoctrination of children from the Saar region (February 16), and the automobile industry (February 16).
- Letters to the French Foreign Minister from Cologne, 1934 March 22-June 9, 9 items. (Box-folder 1:16)
  Includes information on religious opposition of the Nazi Party (March 22, May 12, June 9), Hitler Youth (March 22), popular opinions in the Rhine region (April 18), and the preparation of the Rhine region for war (June 6).
- Letters to the French Foreign Minister from Cologne, 1934 June 11-August 8, 7 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
  Includes information on religious opposition of the Nazi Party (June 11), the rupture of the Nazi regime with the assassination of leaders of the SA (July 12), the assassination of the Chancellor Dollfuss (July 27), and Hitler seizing absolute power (August 3).
- Letters to the French Foreign Minister from Cologne, 1934 September 20-November 15, 16 items. (Box-folder 2:2)
  Includes information on the probability of a military uprising in the Rhine (September 20, September 28), Nazi anti-Semitism (October 9), negative popular opinions in the Rhine region (October 24), religious opposition of the Nazi Party (October 25, November 14, November 15).
- Letters to the French Foreign Minister from Cologne, 1934 December 13-27, 3 items. (Box-folder 2:3)
  Includes information on opposition within the Nazi Party (December 14).
- Letters to the French Foreign Minister from Cologne, 1935 January-April 3, 12 items. (Box-folder 2:4)
  Includes information on the issue of the Saar region (January 9), the rearmament of Germany (January 30), tendencies of the Nazi Party (February 7), placement of a Nazi president in the Rhine region (March 7), and religious arrests (April 3).
- Letters to the French Foreign Minister from Cologne, 1935 April 6-May 30, 11 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
  Includes information on the creation of a new German Calendar (April 6), tendencies of the Nazi Party (April 12), rearmament and military reoccupation of the Rhine region (April 18, April 25, April 27, May 15, May 30), German imports and exports (May 21), and the Russian view of the Nazi Party (May 24).
- Letters to the French Foreign Minister from Cologne, 1935 June 7-November 14, 15 items. (Box-folder 2:6)
  Includes information on meetings with Nazis in which France is assured of Germany's amiable intentions (June 26), religious opposition of the Nazi Party (July 5), the German financial situation (July 31, September 5, September 13, September 18), the anti-Semitic messages of Dr. Schacht-the Minister of the Economy (September 5), and the commercial negotiations with Poland (September 5, September 18).
- Letters to the French Foreign Minister from Cologne, 1936 January-March 18, 17 items. (Box-folder 2:7)
  Includes information on the reestablishment of garrisons in the demilitarized zone (January 22), the growing importance of the army (January 26), the economic crisis (January 29, March 16), religious opposition and Nazi reaction (February 22), preparations made since 1934 for military reoccupation of the Rhine (March 12), and difficulties facing those who live in the Rhine region (March 15).
- Letters to the French Foreign Minister from Cologne, 1936 March 19-June 27, 19 items. (Box-folder 2:8)
  Includes information on the state of the German economy (March 19, March 27), real politik ideology (March 19), the popular opinions of those who live in the Rhine region (March 21), the military reoccupation of the Rhine region (April 4, June 25), preparation of economy for war (April 20, May 18), and German plan to produce synthetic gasoline (June 12).
- Letters to the French Foreign Minister from Cologne, 1936 July 1-December 6, 21 items. (Box-folder 3:1)
  Includes information on the direction of German political affairs (July 3), military secrets (July 9, October 14), rearmament and defense (August 22, October 19, November 14), economic plans (August 25, October 22, November 12, December 6), and the German-Japanese Accord against communism (December 1, December 5).
- Letters to the French Foreign Minister from Cologne, 1937 January-December, 19 items. (Box-folder 3:2)
  Includes information on military recruitment (January 5), the economic situation (February 4, June 10, June 20, June 24, August 5, August 6, August 20), breach of French secret letters (February 18), the involvement of the Catholic Church and Hitler Youth in education (March 8), movement of German troops to Belgian border (June 10), and listening devices installed in French consulate (December 18).
- Letters to the French Foreign Minister from Quito, 1938 January - December, 34 items. (Box-folder 3:3)
  Includes tariff modifications (March 8, March 11, April 15, April 22) and the Franco-Ecuadorian Commercial Convention (June 8, August 2, September 8, November 2).
- Letters to South American Officials, 1938 January-December, 39 items. (Box-folder 3:4)
  Chiefly includes French policy information and answers to other bureaucratic questions.
- Letters to Jean Dobler, 1938 January-1939 September, 9 items. (Box-folder 3:5)
- Diplomatic Invitations, 1938 February-1939, 16 items. (Box-folder 3:6)
  Mainly includes invitations to ambassadorial parties and soirees.
- Letters and Drafts Relating to the Commercial Convention, 1938 March-December, 19 items. (Box-folder 3:7)
  Includes drafts of the agreement (June 8, July 31, August 20, September 14, October 15, October 19).
- Letters to European Officials and Businessmen, 1938 March-December, 24 items. (Box-folder 3:8)
  Chiefly includes information on new governmental policies, the Ecuadorian economy, and tourism.
- Letters to Other South American Ministers, 1938 March-December, 21 items. (Box-folder 3:9)
- Letters to Members of the French Ministry in Ecuador [folder 1], chiefly including the firing of Rafael Leon and bureaucratic instructions, 1938 March-July, 33 items. (Box-folder 3:10)
- Jean Dobler's Personal Financial Accounts, 1938 April-September, 6 items. (Box-folder 3:11)
- Letters to People in Ecuador, 1938 April-August 16, 69 items. (Box-folder 4:1)
  Mostly solving civil matters, visa issues, and telegraph problems.
- Newspaper Article on Jean Dobler from El Comercio, 1938 May 19, 1 item. (Box-folder 4:2)
- Telegrams from Quito, 1938 June-December, 27 items. (Box-folder 4:3)
  Chiefly includes quick instructional notes.
- Letters to Members of the French Ministry in Ecuador [folder 2], 1938 August-December, 23 items. (Box-folder 4:4)
  Chiefly includes the firing of Rafael Leon and bureaucratic instructions.
- Letters to People in Ecuador [folder 2], 1938 August 17- December, 49 items. (Box-folder 4:5)
  Mostly solving civil matters, religious issues visa issues, and telegraph problems.
- Handwritten Notes on the Commercial Convention, 1938 August-October, 29 items. (Box-folder 4:6)
  Includes letter and article drafts.
- Business Cards, A-Z, 1938, 62 items. (Box-folder 4:7)
  Mainly includes government officials and their wives.
- Letters about French Mobilization in Ecuador, 1939 February-November, 44 items. (Box-folder 4:8)
  Chiefly includes letters to the recruitment offices in France about recruitment numbers.
- Photo of French Officials in Guayaquil, 1939 May, 1 item. (Box-folder 4:9)
- Letters Regarding French Recruitment in Ecuador, 1939 August-December, 51 items. (Box-folder 4:10)
  Mainly includes notices to serve and threats to those who have not fulfilled their duty.
- Letters to European Officials and Businessmen, 1939 August-November, 10 items. (Box-folder 4:11)
  Mainly includes Ecuadorian governmental policies.
- Telegrams from Quito, 1939 August-November, 27 items. (Box-folder 4:12)
- Letters to Other South American Ministers, 1939 August-November, 29 items. (Box-folder 4:13)
  Mainly includes information on French mobilization.
- Letters to the French Foreign Minister from Quito, 1939 August-October, 6 items. (Box-folder 4:14)
  Includes a list of foreign men who want to enlist (October 21).
- Letters to People in Ecuador, 1939 September-November, 12 items. (Box-folder 4:15)
  Chiefly includes information on mobilization.
- Letters Regarding Americanismo y Guerra Europea, 1939 September-October, 15 items. (Box-folder 4:16)
  Pamphlet written by Jean Dobler in secret about American Neutrality.